Ruth Lois Hill Papers, 1952-1979
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
Ruth Lois Hill papers
1952-1979
1952-1959
Hill, Ruth Lois, 1906-
MS 234
2 boxes (1 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
YWCA overseas secretary and YWCA executive. The major portion of the collection focuses on Hill's service with the Young Women's Christian Association (YWCA) in Liberia, including detailed letters to her family; correspondence with YWCA officials; reports on her activities in Liberia; plus printed material, memorabilia, postcards and photographs documenting Liberia and YWCA activities there.
1906 Born August 22, Norfolk, Massachusetts
1925-29 Boston University, Bachelor of Arts in Social Science, active in student YWCA
1929 YWCA summer training school for rural secretaries
1929-34 YWCA Secretary, Johnstown, Pennsylvania, worked in towns and cities in the area as Business Girls Traveler's Aide
1934-37 YWCA Group Work Secretary, Brockton, Massachusetts
1937-41 YWCA General Secretary, Billings, Montana
1941-42 Administrator, Mission Center Branch YWCA, San Francisco, California
1945-71 National Board YWCA staff
1945-52 Community Division Staff, Advisory Secretary to small associations in Washington, Oregon, Idaho, Montana, and Wyoming
1952-59 International Division Staff as Advisory Secretary to the YWCA of the Republic of Liberia
1959-63 Eastern Region Staff, New England area, based in New York City
1963-65 Correlator, Southern Region, for nine southern states, based in Atlanta, Georgia
1965-71 Associate Executive Director, Program National Headquarters, New York City
1971 Retired
2005 Ruth Hill died
The Ruth Lois Hill Papers consist of one linear foot of correspondence, reports, memorabilia, printed material, and photographs. The inclusive dates are 1952 to 1979, but the major portion of the material dates from her service with the YWCA in Liberia from 1952 to 1959.
The PERSONAL material consists primarily of letters that Hill wrote home to her mother and her sister, Daisy, from Liberia, 1952-59. These are substantive, personal letters describing in detail her life in Liberia and her work with the YWCA. In addition there is a small quantity of incoming letters from friends, 1959-65.
The PROFESSIONAL series consists of YWCA material contained in three sections: correspondence, reports, and activities. The correspondence consists of letters from I. Beatrice Branch, office secretary, 1954-59; Nancy Randall Martin, Matron, 1959-65; and Clara Davis Brown, National Secretary of the National Board, 1952-65. Also in this section is correspondence with the National Board, 1952-65, which includes Hill's reports to them on her activities in Liberia. The second section consists of reports to the National Board of Directors by the president of the YWCA of Liberia primarily between 1952 and 1962. There are four significant activities included in the third section. Specifically these consist of programs and correspondence related to the United Christian Fellowship Conference, 1953-58, including a Study of the Christian Response in Liberia which was part of the Conference in 1957; programs and correspondence from women's rallies held between 1954 and 1962; Y-Teen activities in 1956; and correspondence about "Fancy Fairs" sponsored between 1959 and 1962. In addition there are programs and correspondence on the farewell party given for Hill before she left Liberia in 1959 and some miscellaneous program material.
The SUBJECTS series contains printed material and postcards saved by Ruth Hill that give a sense of Liberian life in the 1950's.
There are 72 photographs in the PHOTOGRAPHS series. There are eight personal photos of Hill and friends. The remainder consists of YWCA staff and activities.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Personal
II. Professional
III. Subjects
IV. Photographs
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The papers are open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection.
Additional Formats
Selections from the Ruth Lois Hill Papers can be viewed in the Web exhibit "An Ever-Widening Circle of Friendship": YWCA Overseas Secretaries from China to Liberia.
History of the Collection
Ruth Lois Hill donated this collection to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1989.
Search Terms
Hill, Ruth Lois, 1906-; Young Women's Christian Associations--Liberia--History Young Women's Christian Association of the U.S.A.--History; Education--Liberia--History--Sources; Liberia--Description and travel--Sources
- SERIES I. PERSONAL
  - Correspondence
    - Outgoing to family from Liberia, 1952-59 (Box 1, Folder 1-2)
    - Incoming from friends, 1959-65 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Clippings, articles, citations 1954-59, [See also Oversize Materials] (Box 1, Folder 4)
- SERIES II. PROFESSIONAL
  - Correspondence
    - I. Beatrice Branch, 1954-79 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Nancy Randall Martin 1959-65, [See also SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS] (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Clara Davies Brown, 1960-62 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - National Board, 1952-65 (Box 1, Folder 8-10)
  - Reports of the President of the YWCA of Liberia, 1952-62, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Activities
    - United Christian Fellowship Conference, Study of Christian Response in Liberia: programs, reports, correspondence, 1953-58, [See also SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS] (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Women's rallies: programs, correspondence 1954-62, [See also SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS] (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Y-Teens: notes, correspondence, publicity, 1956, [See also SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS] (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Farewell reception for Ruth Hill: programs, correspondence, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Fancy Fair: correspondence, 1959-62 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Miscellaneous activities: printed material, 1957-58, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- SERIES III. SUBJECTS
  - Literacy in Liberia: printed material, 1953-56 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - William V.S. Tubman: printed material, 1955-56 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Liberia: printed material, unused postcards, 1952-56 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS
  - Personal
    - Ruth Lois Hill (4), 1953-59 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Friends (4), 1950-60 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Professional
    - Staff, Board of Directors, and miscellaneous activities (10), 1949-59 (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Christmas party (14), 1952-53, n.d (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - United Christian Fellowship Conference (5), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Women's Rallies (8), 1954-56 (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Y-Teens (3), undated (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - YWCA/YMCA activities (19), 1950s (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Miscellaneous (5), 1950s (Box 2, Folder 29)
- OVERSIZE MATERIALS
  - Citation: Knight Official of the Liberian Humane Order of African Redemption June, 1959 (Map-case Flat File)